<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-01-04T21:10:17+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Clearly Erroneous</title><subtitle>A blog on Data Science and all the rest</subtitle><author><name>Martina Pugliese</name></author><entry><title type="html">Glasgow, I&amp;#8217;m Leaving You!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/glasgow,-I'm-leaving-you!/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Glasgow, I'm Leaving You!" /><published>2016-09-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-09-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/glasgow,-I'm-leaving-you!</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/glasgow,-I'm-leaving-you!/">&lt;p&gt;Actually, at the time of writing this, I’ve already moved on, changed address, left no trace. I moved to Edinburgh. Yea, that happened one week ago.
You must have noticed by now. Yea, I’ve been a coward. And yea, I hear you, I escaped to the rich guy. I didn’t have the heart to tell you before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know there is a fight between you two. You have a certain reputation, Glasgow, and I loved everything about it, from the very start. When you ask people around, they will tell you that you, Glasgow, are the &lt;em&gt;authentic&lt;/em&gt; one and Edinburgh is the &lt;em&gt;postcard-like&lt;/em&gt; one (if they’re on your side). If they’re on the other side, I’m not completely sure what they’d say about you. No, I’m not trying to be nice and sugar-coat the truth, you know I don’t do that. And I’ve so much appreciated when you didn’t do that with me either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to the rich guy. I went to the pretty guy. I feel so bad. But see, things weren’t going to end well: this has been going on for a while just now (you knew) and honestly, going back and forth between you guys is exhausting. I have to have a life, you know. Don’t let me expand too much on the reasons why, I already feel too bad and you wouldn’t get any benefit out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’m going to shut up here and just remember a bit of the many good times we’ve had together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve been very good to me during the (about) year and a half we’ve been together. I’ll always remember this time of my life, it’s been grand!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People say you’re “rough”. No offence (I know you care for your manly reputation), but I think I’ve seen rougher types. Or maybe you only ever showed me your gentle face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;100px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/glasgow-uni.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;glasgow-uni&quot; /&gt; People say you’re “ugly”, especially because they (maybe unconsciously) compare you to Edinburgh, but under the right light, you look just majestic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the Main Building tower of the University (of Glasgow). This picture of you I’ve taken on the very first of our dates, remember that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We both know the “right light” is not something you can take for granted at yours, but hey, when it’s there, it’s just fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;100px&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/kelvingrove-museum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;kelvingrove-museum&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when the sun starts to set after a good day, it’s just magic at the Kelvingrove. You have to value what you have, and it’s sadly true that you appreciate stuff more when it becomes scarce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The affogato at your &lt;a href=&quot;http://avenue.coffee&quot;&gt;Avenue Coffee&lt;/a&gt; is just great. I loved it every time, to the point that it’s been the only thing I’ve ever had in that place. You know I stick to the stuff I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;100px&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/avenue-coffee.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;avenue-coffee&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;100px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/manfield1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;manfield1&quot; /&gt; You know how to make someone smile, like when you just made me find this small pearl in the Manfield Square, near where I used to live and where I passed every time when going to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always had a problem, the drinking. You drink too much, Glasgow. You made me try the finest beers around but see, I just don’t have a taste for alcohol. It’s not my fault. I’m not sure I’m going to solve this problem now (something tells me that I won’t), but look, you definitely had too much of a habit for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;100px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/shilling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;shilling&quot; /&gt; &lt;img height=&quot;100px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/paesano.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;paesano&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shillingbrewingcompany.co.uk&quot;&gt;Shilling Brewery&lt;/a&gt; in the city center is a great place, lots of space, nice people, good environment, even for the weirdos who don’t drink like me. 
Also, you make a mean pizza (as you know, I know something about real pizzas), at &lt;a href=&quot;http://paesanopizza.co.uk&quot;&gt;Paesano Pizza&lt;/a&gt;. It’s well worth the wait you have to endure on a typical Friday night to get a table (no booking allowed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s dozens of other very high-quality places for food and drinks in Glasgow. In fact, everybody knows that your reputation is multi-faceted and you are well known for your restaurants &amp;amp; Co. I’ll let you know if Edinburgh compares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;100px&quot; width=&quot;200px&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/cappaccino.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cappaccino&quot; /&gt; I’ve liked you, even when you pretended you could speak Italian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of language, I’m afrain I have to admit we always had a problem there. True, my comprehension of you has improved, and quite sensibly, but I’m still far from mastering the nuances of your rich jargon vocabulary and the intelligence of your multiple idioms. Plus, the accent. Ah, let’s not forget about the accent. I’ll always end a taxi ride with a headache from the effort to grasp the driver, I think. This problem seems quite softened here. But it was fun, I’ll miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;100px&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/bn1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bn&quot; /&gt; You’re always ready for a laugh and when strolling around you it’s not rare to spot something peculiar. If it’s not an object, it’s someone. You, Glasgow, are really full of life (especially on Friday nights, but this might be a little alcohol-induced, as I told you before).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is not much to explore in you from the superficial point of view (I’m talking about the see-and-go, superficial tourism), there is lots to do and fall in love with when someone gets to know you a little deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;100px&quot; width=&quot;600px&quot; src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/glasgow-snow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;glasgow-snow&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it would be unfair to claim that you’re only good during summer. In fact, winter is when you reveal landscapes like this, which makes me think of Alcott’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little_Women&quot;&gt;Little Women&lt;/a&gt;, not sure why as there’s plenty of other books with snow, but so you know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Glasgow, for giving me lots of memories. Good memories.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martina Pugliese</name></author><summary type="html">Actually, at the time of writing this, I’ve already moved on, changed address, left no trace. I moved to Edinburgh. Yea, that happened one week ago.
You must have noticed by now. Yea, I’ve been a coward. And yea, I hear you, I escaped to the rich guy. I didn’t have the heart to tell you before.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Plotting The Actual Frequencies In A Freqdist In Nltk</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/plotting-the-actual-frequencies-in-a-FreqDist-in-nltk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Plotting The Actual Frequencies In A Freqdist In Nltk" /><published>2016-08-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-08-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/plotting-the-actual-frequencies-in-a-FreqDist-in-nltk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/plotting-the-actual-frequencies-in-a-FreqDist-in-nltk/">&lt;p&gt;Some days ago, trying to visualise a frequency distribution of tokens in a text via NLTK, I was quite surprised (and slightly disappointed) to see that the plot() method of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nltk.org/api/nltk.html#nltk.probability.FreqDist&quot;&gt;FreqDist&lt;/a&gt; class does not support a kwarg for plotting the actual frequencies, rather than the counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the term frequency in NLP is borrowed from Linguistics, where it’s used to mean the counts, not the actual frequency of occurrence of a linguistic something. I personally never quite liked this usage of the word as I find it pretty confusing: a frequency is, typically, a ratio of the occurrences counts of that something to the total of every something in the set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FreqDist is creating a dictionary of counts, not frequencies, which is quite alright. Then you can directly plot them by calling the class method &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nltk.org/api/nltk.html#nltk.probability.FreqDist.plot&quot;&gt;plot()&lt;/a&gt;, without the need to externally call pyplot. I was expecting that among the kwargs allowed by the method there would have been something to normalise said counts to transform them into frequencies. As of NLTK’s version 3.2.1, there isn’t. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nltk.org/api/nltk.html#nltk.probability.FreqDist.freq&quot;&gt;freq(sample)&lt;/a&gt; method gives the frequency of a given sample, but nothing enables the possibility for frequencies to be directly plotted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hack to obtain this is then: What we’re doing here is simply normalising the counts to their sum, paying attention to the fact that N(), which does return this sum, changes when we change the values, so we need to store it beforehand. All the other existing kwargs are preserved for consistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hack to obtain this is then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-py highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;plot_freqdist_freq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                       &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;max_num&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;None&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                       &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cumulative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                       &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;'Frequency plot'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                       &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;linewidth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&quot;
    As of NLTK version 3.2.1, FreqDist.plot() plots the counts 
    and has no kwarg for normalising to frequency. 
    Work this around here.
    
    INPUT:
        - the FreqDist object
        - max_num: if specified, only plot up to this number of items 
          (they are already sorted descending by the FreqDist)
        - cumulative: bool (defaults to False)
        - title: the title to give the plot
        - linewidth: the width of line to use (defaults to 2)
    OUTPUT: plot the freq and return None.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tmp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;copy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;norm&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tmp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;keys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tmp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;float&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;norm&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;max_num&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tmp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;max_num&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cumulative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cumulative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;linewidth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;linewidth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;tmp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;plot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cumulative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cumulative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;linewidth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;linewidth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we’re doing here is simply normalising the counts to their sum, paying attention to the fact that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nltk.org/api/nltk.html#nltk.probability.FreqDist.N&quot;&gt;N()&lt;/a&gt;, which does return this sum, changes when we change the values, so we need to store it beforehand. All the other existing kwargs are preserved for consistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;75px&quot; width=&quot;450px&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/freqdist.png&quot; alt=&quot;freqdist&quot; /&gt; The result is in figure, for the text of Austen’s Sense and Sensibility (available as a book in the NLTK data), we’re plotting the frequency of the 50 most frequent tokens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like to is the most frequent token (note that no pre-processing/removals have been employed), with a frequency of around 6.5%. Having this number might be much more interesting than the count (which is around 9000, for reference).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Martina Pugliese</name></author><summary type="html">Some days ago, trying to visualise a frequency distribution of tokens in a text via NLTK, I was quite surprised (and slightly disappointed) to see that the plot() method of the FreqDist class does not support a kwarg for plotting the actual frequencies, rather than the counts.</summary></entry></feed>
